Welcome to AP US History Unit 9, which
is the last unit. This unit will simply
cover the time period 1980 to the
present in American history, and it is
pretty short, meaning it will only be
worth 4 to 6% on your AP exam. This
video will simply be a clipped-together
video of all my Unit 9 topic review
videos without the AP style questions at
the end of each video. If you'd like to
try the questions at the end of the
videos, my full APUSH Unit 9 playlist
will be in the description. Really
quickly, I just want to mention that on
this channel, there will likely be live
reviews for this course at the end of
the year. If you'd be interested in
attending, as the exams get closer, the
dates and times of these live streams
will be released on my Instagram. So, go
make sure to follow that. Anyway, let's
get into the final unit of AP US
History.
So, in our last unit, we've established
that by the '80s, citizens of America
have lost confidence in the greater
American government for a variety of
reasons. So, now coming back into this,
people start to think maybe the
government is the problem, not the
solution. And that right there is the
opening for conservatives. Enter Ronald
Reagan. He will argue that the
government is too big, taxes are too
high, regulations hurt businesses,
welfare programs don't actually fix
poverty, and that society needs more,
quote, traditional values. And after
Ronald Reagan gets elected, pretty
quickly an economic system called
Reaganomics is enacted. This is broken
into three parts. First, you [music]
have tax cuts, meaning that people plus
businesses keep more money. The second
here is deregulation, meaning that there
will be fewer government rules on
industries. And finally, you have
supply-side economics, where helping
businesses grow is supposed to help
everyone, meaning more jobs, more goods,
and a stronger economy overall. But
anyway, I'm sure you were wondering
whether or not this is a good or bad
idea. Well, it's not really my place to
say. Rather, what I will do here is
objectively explain what both political
sides thought of this, and you can
decide whether it's good or bad
yourself. Conservatives would argue that
Reaganomics would grow the economy, make
inflation go down, and allow businesses
to expand, but the liberals on the other
hand would argue Reaganomics basically
mostly benefited the rich and would
cause the wealth gap in the US deficit
to grow. And also, something important
to note is that even though Reagan
wanted a smaller government, programs
like Social Security and Medicare
stayed, along with an increased military
spending, so the government really stays
a similar size. But before I end this
video, I want to mention that this rise
of conservatism was very impactful,
mostly because the 1980s wasn't even
that long ago. Modern politics to this
day still debate ideologies from the
'80s and beyond. And also, these
conservative '80s weren't even totally
political. You will also see evangelical
Christians rise into supporting and
aligning with the conservative side. So,
now it has a clear social effect. Hey
there. Do you remember that whole Cold
War thing that has been going on for a
while now? Well, it actually is going to
end in this video with the collapse of
the Soviet Union. Now, really quickly, I
want to say that the dissolution of the
Soviet Union is a very complex topic,
and there is way too many reasons for
it. So, just understand that this video
might be an oversimplification. But
anyway, historians often like to blame
three people for the Soviet Union's
collapse: Ronald Reagan, Pope John Paul
II,
and Mikhail Gorbachev. For Reagan's
side, the US will build a massive
military with increased spending,
focusing on defending against nuclear
missiles, and the program here was
called SDI, or the nickname Star Wars.
Reagan also pushed strong anti-communist
rhetoric, even going as far to call the
Soviet a, quote, evil empire. In fact,
let's roll that clip. To ignore the
facts of history and the aggressive
impulses of an evil empire.
Apply ice to the burned area, my
goodness. And finally, the last thing
here is that Reagan eventually worked
with the Soviet Union in a series of
meetings to reduce tensions. [music]
But moving on, for Pope John Paul II,
he helped push anti-communist beliefs in
Poland and ignited a massive solidarity
movement, which was a big blow to the
Soviet Union. But the final person here,
and probably the most important, is
Mikhail Gorbachev, who was the leader of
the Soviet Union starting in 1985.
Basically, Gorbachev is not like his
predecessors. He was instead a lot less
strict. And by this point, the USSR is
struggling to keep up financially with
the US. In response, Gorbachev releases
government reforms that attempt to fix
society, but instead totally weaken the
Soviet government. [music] And finally,
countries controlled under the Soviet
Union begin to break away until 1989,
where the Berlin Wall officially falls,
and a few years later, the Soviet Union
collapses, ending the Cold War. So, now
I want you to think about something.
Since there is no more USSR rival, the
US is going to be the most powerful
nation in the world. And after this,
it's also important to note the US is
still going to intervene around the
world for various reasons like
peacekeeping and regional conflicts. And
now, I am sure you can imagine lots of
different debates about the US's role in
the world will start up. Lots of people
throughout the last century in American
history have been working in factories.
I mean, it was the whole point of the
Gilded Age. But now, with the Cold War
mostly over, countries, with a specific
emphasis on China, are going to open up
to trade. So, that begs the question: if
it is cheaper to globalize and pay
Chinese workers to produce goods, rather
than paying a lot of money to American
workers, why the heck would any business
stay localized in America? And this will
lead to one of the biggest shifts in
world history called globalization,
where businesses operate globally,
meaning companies can produce goods in
other countries, and there is a big
trade increase. And pretty quickly,
looking at the United States, factory
jobs dry up relatively quickly. And now
you see new age technology come out at a
very crucial point. So, that means now
after the '80s, the US job market will
shift to mostly encapsulate service
jobs, meaning things like retail,
healthcare, finance, education, or tech.
This means how people work, how
businesses operate, and how people
communicate all drastically changed in a
brief period. This also means that labor
unions dramatically decline alongside
factory jobs. want to point out that
this new technology, like the internet
and computers, really does change
everything. For example, later you have
social media, along with stuff like
remote work becoming a possibility. You
also see a spike in production because
new technology makes it so workers can
produce more in less time. But wherever
there is light, there is also darkness.
And here I want to talk about the bad
effects of this new generation. The
first here is that wages for middle and
working-class Americans stagnated, as
most economic gains increasingly went to
corporations and the top 1%. The second
thing here, though, is a digital divide.
Because I want you to imagine that lots
of older folks who aren't prone to
changing their ways, or might not have
access to the new tech, could
potentially not adopt the new
technological changes. So, that means
some people benefit a lot from the new
tech economy, while many others are left
behind. Hey, quick question. Do you like
being cold? I personally don't really
like it, and a lot of Americans actually
agree with me, which is why in the
1980s, millions of Americans will
migrate to the Sun Belt. being hotter
temperatures and opportunities, which
will cause these regions to gain more
political power. But moving on, after
1965, when that whole immigration act
was passed, immigration steadily rose
following the '60s. But then you see it
spike like crazy in the 1980s. And this
happens because of a collection of
things. The first thing is that the US
enacted the Refugee Act of 1980, which
just simply adopted a humanitarian
approach to admitting and resettling
refugees. But the bigger thing here is a
whole lot of bad things around the world
happened all at once. For example,
Mexico and Cuba both go through an
economic crisis. El Salvador, Guatemala,
and Nicaragua all go through civil wars.
Communism will force thousands to flee
from Vietnam, Cambodia, and Laos, and
Iran also goes through a revolution. And
many people also left the Philippines,
Korea, and India. Now, you don't need to
necessarily memorize these all. I just
want to show you that a lot of stuff
happened all at once, which caused so
many different immigrants to enter the
United States in the 1980s. The big
effect you see here is what our society
has become now in the present. America
is so culturally diverse as a country
that there are so many bilingual
communities and lots of culture from
other countries, I am sure you see all
over the place. And another big effect
of this is that immigrants will often
fill many blue-collar jobs, meaning
manual labor-based jobs, in America. But
the other big thing this leads to is the
modern debate surrounding immigration.
Things like border control, legal versus
illegal immigration, bilingual
education, and the more complex
assimilation versus multiculturalism.
Welcome to the last topic of AP US
History in under 3 minutes. My intro
here will just be to simply say thank
you to you all for a wonderful year
together, and let's get into it. So, not
to be abrupt here, but 9/11. It is an
event we all know. Planes will crash
into the World Trade Center and the
Pentagon in a coordinated terrorist
attack carried out by the group
Al-Qaeda. This is shocking to the US at
the time, and it is a very unprecedented
event. And so, the US response to this
will be to enact a war on terror. And if
you are like me and wonder how exactly
you can enact a war on an ideology,
well, really what the war on terror was
was a war in Afghanistan, targeting the
terrorist group responsible for 9/11,
Al-Qaeda, and the Taliban government
that supported the group. And also, the
war on terror expanded to Iraq for
reasons originally justified by claims
of weapons of mass destruction. It's
also important to note that the US
depended a lot on oil coming from the
Middle East. And so, a lot of
complications arose over energy because
of the military actions happening in
that region. So, the US shifts. They
don't have Cold War enemies anymore.
Their big enemy now is instead [music]
terror. And this will even expand to the
home front with the Patriot Act, where
the US expanded law enforcement
surveillance powers and strengthened
measures against terrorism financing. If
you were a supporter of this act, you
might note the need to keep Americans
safe, but critics of this act might say
this violates civil liberties and
privacy [music] rights. But anyway, for
one last time, let's look at the US.
What can we say at the end of this
[music] course? Well, the US is the most
powerful nation in the world. That is
pretty objective. The US will continue
to intervene internationally, influence
global politics, and lead economically
and militarily. My goodness, the
curriculum here really makes me glaze
the heck out of the US. Whatever. And
that is it for the entire course of AP
US history. I think you get the gist
here with following my other channel,
but I just want to let you all know that
it has been a blast this year to cover
US history with all you guys. Thank you
for everything once again. I hope to see
you in the live streams. I also hope for
you to all get a five on this exam, and
it has been an honor.